[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se - radio dotnet. SC radio brings you.
relevant and detailed discussions of software engineering topics at least once a month.
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E software magazine online at computer org slash software.
hello this is Josh Wong for software engineering radio.
today I have with me Cedric shampoo. Cedric is a committer of the open source groovy language.
and he's currently working for Gradle an innovative scalable build system that internally uses Govi.
he wrote a number of the recent improvements of the language including static compilation a templating engine.
and more recently he introduced Android support.
he's an open source advocate and a member of the Apache Software Foundation.
hi Cedric welcome to software engineering radio.
do you have anything you want to add to that bio?
hi, no, I think it's pretty complete no thanks.
well, thanks for joining us welcome to software engineering video.
we own the software engineer a do podcast like to explore old languages and new ones alike.
and goofy of course has been around for a long time.
can you tell us about how and when groovy was created? yeah, sure.
so groovy was created more than 10 years ago actually.
so in 2003 by gemser Strachan.
so at that time it was a language one of the first language on the JVM apart from Java basically.
so he wanted to create a dynamic language for a JVM inspired by languages like Ruby.
but something that would be closer to to Java to what the Java developers had in mind.
and it was it was a pretty innovative idea at that time.
because not many things were done on the JVM apart from Java.
and having the idea of creating something dynamic for the JVM was at that time very innovative.
and probably a crazy idea.
and yeah, I think today it's more than ten years then the language has been created.
it's used really in a lot of different contexts.
and very recently sir just at the beginning of this year the language just joined the Apache Software Foundation.
so it's not really a language which is backed by very well-known open-source foundations.
something that is really leaning towards the future.
did the language live at a sort of foundation before?
so before it was really a language created by I would say geeks basically.
so it was a language developed during the the weekends.
but it was so impressive what it could do that it really became evident.
that you could have support professional support for it.
so I think it was in 2008 that a company was created which.
was called gt1 at that time.
by a game LaForge Graham Roche and Alex TaqMan at that time.
and those guys were really wanted really wanted to create something to support the development of the language.
so before 2008 the language was created and developed in a totally open-source fashion.
and starting from - 2008 it was company backed.
and yeah, gt1 later was acquired by Springs host and VMware eventually people fall.
and it's really recently so at the beginning of the year that people ended sponsorships.
of a follow up for for that language and that we moved to a foundation.
but technically the language existed before founding of companies.
so it was an open-source project from the beginning.
and it's still an open-source project developed now part of the Apache Software Foundation.
and has they moved the foundation increased or the finished interest and activity around the language and ecosystem?
so it I would say it really interested more people like Tony.
because before that some people were not really wanted to to use groovy just because it was company backed.
so they were thinking that if the company removed money and removed from the offending.
the language could disappear.
and it's true that we have seen some resonant project disappearing just because the company stopped funding the project.
so because we moved to the Apache Software Foundation now we see more people on a mailing list.
asking to help developing the language.
so we still don't have released anything yet and the de foundation.
because we have some yeah technical process to follow.
you know we're in something which is called the incubator.
and we have to make sure that we follow the release process etc basically.
I think that now that we're in the foundation more companies will be interested in investing into the language.
and it will not be seen anymore as the product of pivotal or before being where etc.
so a lot of interest actually yeah.
very good the original language was is it fair to say that it.
was designed to look or feel sort of like Java at the time?
totally yeah, and I think it's still true actually.
the so the language Burroughs the syntax of Java.
so it makes different semantics of on top of that.
but basically if you know Java if you know the language Java you know how to programming groovy.
so you can almost copy and paste java code and it will compile as groovy code.
so there are some subtle differences in the syntax.
but in the beginning the language was really made to work with the Java grammar.
so one question of course would be if it is the same syntax why is it a different language?
and it is a different language because it adds a lot on top of Java.
so it adds a lot but I would say it also removes a lot. it removes a lot of boilerplate.
Thank You Annie sir. so in the very beginning for example for those of you who are aware of what a closure is.
groovy added closures since day one.
so we had some functional programming features in the groovy language in the right beginning of the creation of the language.
really much before Java actually they did the same in Java eight basically.
but the trivy had that since day since day one.
I understood that up to a point you could take Java 7 code and and paste it into a goofy file.
and then run that is that still true with lambdas or is there interchangeability there?
no, so because of that closure syntax in the lambda syntax.
so in Java 8 we have the lambda syntax which is for those functional interfaces.
and the syntax is very close to what groovy has it's not the same.
but it also has some very different semantics from the closures.
so today you cannot copy Java 8 code in groovy.
just because we don't support lambda syntax.
and we don't support it yet because we want to make sure we made the right decision regarding the semantics of lambdas in groovy.
so it's not that we will not support it.
it's really that we want to make sure we make the right decision regarding support for that.
and at any rate as you say the language is the two of them when compared to each other. it's pretty easy to translate?
yes, yeah, I love to say that basically if you take some Java classes.
you remove a lot of the boilerplate code and you have groovy.
so that's really you you remove most of the velocity of the language.
for example we know that it's really simple examples.
but in Java 99% of classes or methods are public.
and groovy by default it would be public so you can remove a keyword that's an example.
you can remove all the semicolons for example really something that you don't need.
or if you have you know some it's it's an something that we also see very often in Java code.
it's something like if X instance of something then you have to cast inside if.
just to be able to call the methods in groovy you don't have to do that etc etc.
so it's really removing all the the code which is not necessary.
and we have some wonderful meta programming.
capabilities to help and doing that. is the you just mentioned you don't have to cast does that mean that cuvee is loosely typed or what does that mean?
so it's yeah, so it's a dynamic language at the beginning.
what I had done in the fasting last a few years is a static version of the language.
so you have the two options actually.
so you have strong typing so groovy is a strongly typed language. but it's also dynamic.
so when you don't have to cast it's actually because you fall back on the dynamic runtime.
so when a method is invoked it is invoked based on the room type runtime types sorry.
so say you don't you want to call the method foo and an object.
then difference very different from the Java a way of invoking methods.
because you will take the object and check at run time if it has a few method.
so for those of you who are familiar with languages like small talk it's really similar.
because you have a made-up protocol finding how a method should be invoked.
and this is runtime metaprogramming.
so groovy Felisa builds that so totally of the right the behavior of invoking methods at runtime.
and really it doesn't mean that it's not typed it is strongly typed.
and it it is really because we have strong types that we're capable of handling that.
so it was one of the maybe I would say problems.
that some Java developers had with groovy because they were familiar with compile time errors.
for example if you try to invoke a method which doesn't exist on an object statically.
they didn't have any compile time error.
because we will let you define for example the behavior of an object if it doesn't have a method.
so if you call a method that doesn't exist you can still do something which is very useful for some cases.
we can talk about that later if you want.
and that was a problem.
so for some people at least some are very familiar for the Ruby guys.
it's really something that they're familiar with but for Java developers it's really surprising behavior.
so we added a static a fully static note groovy.
that mimics basically what Java does with more even more type inference.
that what javis capable of doing.
and in that case you have really the same behavior between groovy and Java with strongly typed features.
and I would say that it's even more pleasant to use groovy in that case.
because of the advanced type inference that groovy provides.
so this type inference and this extra succinct or you know very clean syntax.
that you're describing does that mean that goo V lends itself to sort of scripting as well?
yes, so there are multiple use cases for groovy.
so the first history query the first use cases were really scripting.
because one of the key points of groovy is that you have groovy scripts.
and a groovy script is basically what you would write in a Java class in the main class.
a main method of a main class.
and when I talked about boilerplate code it's really that you know in Java.
if you want to write something and just Tet test a few lines of code.
you have to create the class and main method and inside you have to write that code.
in groovy you don't have to do that.
you just write the main body and it's executable as a script.
so it was one of the main use cases of groovy.
and yeah you were saying that I will raid also Gradle is a build system that uses groovy internally.
and you have build scripts and those build scripts are written in groovy.
and the difference between those scripts those build scripts and a groovy script in general.
is that actually the build scripts of Gradle are what we call a DSL.
so it's a domain-specific language built to create builds.
so in the case of Gradle of course.
but groovy is really good at designing what we called ear cells.
so for those of you who are not familiar with notion of DSL it's basically it's really simple.
if you take sequel for example sequel is a DSL.
so it's a it's a language that you design for one thing which is querying a database.
and in the case of Gradle we have a DSL which is aimed at writing build scripts.
and groovy is really it's really really good at writing the essence. design the essence.
and historically I I started groovy using groovy myself in the case of a DSL that.
was designed for linguists.
and at that time so when I started working with groovy what was really interesting is that I could design a language.
so domain-specific language for those people those linguist.
and they didn't know anything about programming.
and what they had in front of them the file the contents of the file was something that they could read.
they didn't have any class inside they didn't have any method call.
or something that looked like a method call in the eyes of a programmer.
and still they were using a programming language without knowing.
and I really appreciated that because groovy makes it easy.
and in the end what what you have that DSL is compiled into something which is JVM bytecode.
so you can still have the performance of JVM bytecode.
and that's really something that really groovy is very good at.
interesting so does this mean that you can.
if I Israel way to evaluate groovy code live interactively?
yes, so we have yet we have multiple tools for that.
so one use case would be well we really talk about DevOps those days.
and for system administrators or whatever it's often very practical to have some scripts that you can execute.
and sometimes just to design the script it's really useful to have some kind of ripple. so it's an read evaluation loop.
and you just write code and it executes as you write it.
it's really really useful to design.
so groovy offers that so you have a ripple.
but that is the interactive mode of generating code.
so basically when you do that you have the code which is compiled and executed as you write it.
this is one case and the other one which is interesting.
in I would say much more used in the in the reality by people who use groovy.
is that you can create and instantiate scripts at runtime.
so during the application lifecycle after it has been compiled.
you can still come scripts and execute them at runtime.
so you really have the option to compile code at runtime.
so who did the two aspects of the dynamic code execution I see?
so can you can you take these scripts and then run them directly?
and if so today do they get compiled is there a way to trigger the compilation directly?
or you know a place?
yes, yes, so you have the two options.
so one one is due to just stay with scripts scripts everywhere.
that means that when you execute the scripts this passed it is compiled and it generates JVM bytecode.
so I think it's important to understand that that when you have a script a groovy script it's really not interpreted. it is compiled.
so you have all the faces that you have in almost all compiled languages.
which is you pass everything you generate an abstract syntax tree.
and then the abstract syntax tree is compiled down to bytecode.
and then executed by the virtual machine or the the runtime the language runtime whatever it is. and groovy has that.
so if you have groovy scripts you can execute for example groovy my script a groovy.
and it will do all that compile the script execute it.
but it it is really one aspect of the language.
and the other one is that you can write full applications in groovy.
and in that case you don't want to recompile everything every time you run the application.
usually what you want to do is do what you have with Java code with C++ code etc.
so with compiled languages which is you compile the code generates the classes.
and in the end what you deliver is a binary file you execute application.
and groovy allows you to to mix both aspects.
you can have those compiled classes pre-compiled classes.
and you can have those script form classes is that is that pre-compiled?
is there like a GU VC or something like this?
yes, so you have a groovy C compiler which is integrated with the most build tools that we have today in JVM world.
so that's yeah you have the groovy see come on line to you you have an ant plugin.
you have a maven plug-in and of course we have a cradle plugin.
so it's really natural to integrate groovy into your Java Java projects.
and I would even say that on the JVM there's probably not any other language.
that makes it so easy to mix groovy and German well groovy or whatever language it is with the Java code.
so you can use Java classes in groovy code.
but you can also use groovy classes in Java code and there you can really mix.
you can write one class in Java when class in groovy and one called the other.
and it's not problem or for groovy you have what we call a joint compiler.
that will do the job of mixing the code.
it's it's really interesting for that.
because it means that you can start writing an application either in Java or groovy and mixing languages.
and it's really in the you know today we talk about polyglots applications.
and it's really that spirit you can have an application written in many languages.
and groovy makes it very easy to integrate with Java actually.
you mentioned earlier that the language provides all the usual phases as a compiled like language like Java.
because of the sort of PLAs plastic nature of of the language describe.
are there are other ways to to act on the code in other phases?
can I do things for example with the ast tree like like I could with a with the Lisp for example?
yes, so groovy provides the two aspects we have metaprogramming in general.
and we have the trust by submitter programming.
one is the runtime at a programming.
and the other one which is something I really like is the compile time meta programming. so runtime meta programming.
is basically you can at runtime decide to add methods at runtime.
so you have an object and you will decorate it with new methods.
or you can change the behavior of calling some method at runtime.
so that's what inspects.
but since it's a compiled language and that we have access to that abstract syntax tree.
actually we can also do some compile time at a programming.
which is the methods instead of being added for example at come at runtime you can add them at compile time.
and it is very important in case you want to have that interaction with Java classes for example.
because say that you want to create a class that generates new methods.
if you do it at runtime the Java object will not see those methods.
because Java is a statically compiled language.
so if a method is not defined at compile time it will not let you call it of course.
because it has to know ahead of time.
so groovy will let you do some compile time meta programming.
so we call that in groovy we call that a ast transforms or ast transformations.
so it's abstract syntax tree transformations.
so it means that we have passed that script we have an internal representation of the of the program.
which is the abstract syntax tree.
and we can manipulate that tree to add some methods to create in classes to do whatever you want.
and this is very powerful because everything that you have is generated into bytecode.
which makes visible to all the languages so be Java Scala whatever you want.
so you can call all those methods all those classes generated at runtime.
so for those of you who are familiar with Java.
a good example of an AST transformation that we often use is the two string or equals and hashcode.
so those in groovy our instance forms.
so that's basically an annotation that you put on your class.
and once you've done that.
the two string method is generated for you.
the equals and hashcode methods are generated for you.
so when we say that groovy reduces the boilerplate.
it also reduces all the common code that you have to write.
but you feel that it is wrong to write that go because really the compiler could do it for you.
you know generating to string is really often just for debugging.
it should be on use for leveling it's not always the case but anyway.
and that code you don't care to write it you know it's just you have to.
so an annotation can generate it for you.
so groovy provides an annotation to do it.
and yeah, it's the same for equals and hashcode.
and probably another example in the case of design patterns would be the delegate design pattern.
that we often find Java which is you have a class and you delegate to another classical.
and actually in groov it's super easy to do.
because you just annotate a member of your class with the at delegate annotation.
and then it will generate all the delegation methods for you.
which is also interesting because if you change the delegate type and you add a new method.
you didn't have to change the class which uses the delegate annotation the compiler will do it for you.
so it's really really interesting powerful all those methods will be visible from the Java side.
Wow, yeah, does this does this do these ast transforms play into the the DSL that. you've described?
the capabilities yourselves and where are where are they used?
what kind of dsl x' beside the cradle for example?
yes, Gradle is one for the build system.
so you have a very nice declarative syntax to declare while build is what the dependencies are.
if you compare for example they did a groovy Gradle script actually with a maven XML file.
you will you will see that it's much more human readable.
just because you have that hero key and you know scoped descriptive means of yeah describing the build.
but that's really one example.
but in case of age transformations I think the best example that you can find.
of something that does very I would say crazy transformations and groovy codes probably Spock.
so SPARC is a test framework so for groovy but also for Java code.
so you can use poke even if you want to test Java classes.
so that's sort of like what you were mentioning earlier the polyglot programming?
yes, yes, so we have a testing framework which is called Spock.
so you write your classes your test classes in groovy.
but you can test what is under test is actually Java code or groovy code.
this kind of code you don't care really what you want to test.
it's really the syntax of Spock which is pretty crazy.
and you can have method names for example that have spaces inside.
so you can have something like Def and you open the double quotes and say.
def should create a new database connection and that's the name of your method.
and inside you will have some label saying given something when a connection is created.
then you expect something sets some kind of B avy grievin development tool.
and that makes everything incredibly readable and feel.
for those of you who use J unit testing G moving back to that.
once you've tasted Spock is really awful.
because SPARC really makes it so easy to read the tests and the syntax is very nice for that.
and it's totally based on these two transformations of groovy code.
because if you take a Spock it's called a specification the test and Spock is is really. specification is that the same as sort of a behavior driven development?
sorry, yes spec it but but you can use it for balls unit testing and more integration tests whatever.
it's it's it's a bit larger than just behavior driven development.
and yet if you take just a specification of the code.
and that you try to compile it just as groovy code without Spock it will fail compilation.
and at runtime it would just fail.
and the reason is that Spock internal use in tasty transformation.
to transform the code would have the met the method bodies do something which is actually doing the tests.
so it's crazy really crazy what it is capable of doing.
and it makes it very very pleasant to test code in JVM ecosystem.
sounds very powerful it is.
does to these ast transforms and is this meta programming.
and generally all these capabilities that you describe that sound like they let you add new syntax.
or radically change existing syntax to those features are they well supported in IDE s?
so it depends I would say.
that if you rely runtime meta programming.
basically unless you explain to the IDE what your DSL is supposed to do.
it will not know the behavior of the code is it's a runtime thing. so the ID will not know.
so in eclipse or IntelliJ you have some DSL descriptors that you can write.
and what is funny is that those descriptors are also written groovy.
so it's a it's a DSL and groovy to describe the geocells.
some kind of meet RDF else.
and once you've written that you can have ID support.
so you can describe to the IDE what your diesel is supposed to do.
so that is if you use runtime metaprogramming.
and one is interesting feature of the languages itself.
if you use static the static mode of the language which again is really something optional.
you don't have to it's by default it's not statically compiled.
it's not the static mode of review is enabled but if you do you you can enable.
so very powerful features and one of them is the type checking extensions.
and may sound scary but it's really not.
the static type checking extensions in groovy will let you plug into the type checking of groovy.
and you will be able to explain to the compiler what you are doing.
and that makes it very powerful.
because yeah you were talking about the templating engine that groovy introduced recently.
and it's it uses that feature of time tracking extensions.
and basically what you have is a syntax which is build the license ax.
so you have HTML then open in brackets and inside you have body opening brackets etc.
so it's code which looks like regular groovy code build alike.
but it is compiled statically and it stunts late.
and actually the compiler doesn't know anything about a method called HTML.
and it doesn't know about the method called P for paragraph o or a for links.
but you can explain to the compiler okay if there is method that you don't know about.
okay I as the designer of the DSL I know what it does.
and actually each will call a method which is for example create HTML node which is the name HTML extent.
and you can describe what the method is going to be called.
what method is going to be cool and what is the type of the return type of that method call.
so you can really describe and plug into the in the type checking system of the groovy language.
just to enhance what is capable of doing at compile time.
so you have like method missing but even yet powerful.
because now you can say type missing. yes, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
so you have I'm not saying that it is easy to do that it is possible to do it.
and once you've done that.
you can really have very compact and very performant DSL implementation.
because you do not rely on rim time anymore you can do everything statically.
and you can really switch form from a node where methods are decided at one time.
from something which is decided at compile time.
so everything is known before you execute the code.
so it's really yeah really interesting.
and you can have some ID supports for the generated methods for that. so wow, it's pretty cool.
yep, so far we've talked about how dynamic this languages in terms of the syntax that it can support.
the the ways that you can express concepts.
it sounds like if you're a Java developer used to basic Java syntax.
than goofy will view just as welcoming as if you are a an advanced developer.
who wants to really really use the meta programming.
capabilities to their fullest.
yeah, is there I guess Spock is one use case Gradle certainly is another other other yet?
so it's one of the biggest use cases of groovy today's greys.
Grey's is a web framework that was originally inspired by rails.
and it's yeah it's some kind of a problem today.
because people tend to think that race is just Ruby and rays but for the Java ecosystem.
but grace is really much more than that.
Graves is a web framework a full stack web framework.
but it also provides some micro-services capabilities.
so you can design either microservice or a full stack application.
you can design web services with a if you want HTML backends.
but you can also design REST API is whatever.
and grace is all about the plug-in system.
so it is powerful just because of the plug-in system.
and you can really make it very pleasant to design where that vacations on the Java ecosystem just using grace.
it's just because it will rely on the meta programming. features of groovy.
to remove all the boilerplate that you have to get you to write.
so just an example if you want you have a controller you would either annotate it with at controller.
or implements an interface and it will automatically generate all the backend method for that.
so if if you have a rest endpoint it will generate the rest endpoint etc etc.
and it's really really easy it's just a few lines of code to create something.
ah, so when you're using it like that does it feel like a very clean and sort of light Java?
or does it feel like a completely different DSL?
so the classes look very much like Java but without all the bullet blade code again.
so you have all those classes so it's really readable for those of you who are familiar with Java.
that you really focus on what you want focus you you don't have to worry about creating all those.
yeah all those wiring that you have to create for a typical web application Java.
especially if you think of GE you know so everything is wired automatically.
you don't have to annotate anything it's really byte convention.
if it finds something in one place it will generate the code for you.
so if you have a class which isn't the control source repository it will know that it is a controller. without having to do anything.
so it's really leveraging the the conventions to to make it much more concise.
ah, sorry so it looks and feels very similar again as you say to a to a Java without all the boilerplate.
it doesn't look like a different language altogether?
no, it's not too far you could easily come into it from there yeah.
as you become more advanced maybe you do great oh and Spock exactly.
and I would say that often often people at least coming from Java.
start writing groovy as they write java code.
so it's really easy to find if you look at groovy code and you find a class which is written like Java.
you know it's big enough wrote that because you have older.
you will find all the public modifiers you will find semicolons everywhere.
you will have all the parenthesis because yang reviews some some of the parentheses are optional.
you don't have to put them so you you see that.
and eventually as you can expertise in the language you start removing all which is not necessary.
and you you end up with something which is very clear to read.
and I think that is really what one of them key selling points of groovy is.
that you can take that Java code and migrate slowly to something which is more VD or not it.
I see you've described several different modes of use as a script as a ripple as a pre-compiled class.
you've described that the language itself can be very lacks.
with the sort of decisions about which types are in place.
or they can be very strict because you have this static mode.
how does the language what is it what are the language characteristics with with regard to performance?
I mean is it comparable to Java or does it is it more comfortable to like a ruby or Python?
or maybe faster than Java are the ways to optimize?
so yeah, there are multiple aspects of performance.
so here in general what I say to people is that you don't care about the performance of the language. until you have a problem.
so because often people tend to say okay groovy slow so I will not use it and it's an error.
because often what is low is really did the database access or I or whatever.
that's one aspect but technically you have several options in groovy. so we have multiple runtimes.
so you have the runtime which is dynamic runtime fully dynamic runtime.
and we have static compilation.
so in case you static compilation basically the performance is the same as Java code.
so it's yeah morale is the same.
it can be sometimes a bit faster sometimes a bit slower but same performance.
it's very different if you use the runtime metaprogramming features and dynamic runtime.
so in that case we have we have two runtimes actually four groovy.
because groovy was created yeah in 2003.
and at that time there wasn't any supports in the JVM for dynamic runtimes.
so groovy does a lot of magic into biker to be able to perform dynamic calls.
so it uses reflection internally but not only reflection.
it uses also dynamic generation of code.
so you have classes generated at runtime just to make it faster to execute code.
does that use something like CG lib?
it doesn't use it really but uses ASM which is the library that we used to generate by code.
that's very similar in concept to to what CT lab does.
it's just that city lab is more suitable for proxies basically.
you can create you that we have some more general use cases for that.
so we directly generate bike on using the acing library.
so we do that in the traditional run time their legacy run time.
and since actually the release of Java 7.
Java 7 introduced a new bytecode instruction in the Java ecosystem which is called invokedynamic.
and that is really a revolution for dynamically languages like us.
and it is also revolution for Java itself.
because if you knew the land as in Java 8 actually learners use in fact dynamic internally.
so the JVM itself uses dynamic invocation.
and tell me without you the developer knowing that.
and that new instruction led us to develop an alternative runtime for groovy.
which is based on invoke dynamic.
so depending on the target JVM that you have.
you can either use the legacy runtime which is enabled still enabled by default today.
or the invokedynamic runtime if use Java 7 or more.
and the the performance of the invoke dynamic runtime should be better.
it's not always the case just because when Java 7 was out was very buggy and not optimized.
and it's much better now with Java 8.
because since they use it internally for for falender's they had to improve the performance of invoke dynamic.
so if you use the invitar ammok runtime of groovy and the java 8.
you will probably see a really good performance boost in in groovy performance for the dynamic runtime I.
think. but in any case to give you an ID.
even if you take the legacy rundown on the invoke dynamic runtime.
is still much faster than what you can have Ruby for example.
even if you use even really even if you use do you know the dynamic runtime.
I see so that's that's interesting the invoke dynamic thing.
is something that came from the Java ecosystem and influenced some of the design in newer versions of GUI.
have we have we seen other features that have influenced or changed the way groovy works?
and perhaps more more interestingly are there features from groovy that have influenced Java?
yes, so it's really for VAT dye Namek is really languages like groovy orange a ruby.
who which in first Java actually.
because it is because there were dynamic languages on the daemon like Jade Rubio on groovy.
that the designers of those languages asked JVM guys to create something.
to make it easier to create dynamic runtimes.
and it make it made it very very easy to to design something on top of that.
and the JVM designers took all the needs that we had to create a dynamic runtime for for groovy.
and they extended that something which is more useable to more contexts.
in this case the lambdas.
but it's really something that you can have that you can see as an end user without knowing.
and I would say that for Java 8 I know yeah.
when when you take a look at the lambda syntax it's really actually close to what you have in groovy.
it uses a different syntax that the concept of lambdas is very similar to the concept of closures that we had.
so it would be yeah it would be probably difficult to say that really influenced Java in that situation.
that it's really something which is yeah influencing in some way.
I see has do you think there are other languages that have been influenced or been guided by something like groovy?
yes sir, so recently if you know the Swift programming language for iOS.
and yeah even desktop no applications on on the Mac ecosystem.
yeah Apple ecosystems are Swift.
it's really language that took from modern languages like groovy Scala.
and it has some features which are directly inspired from Groovy's.
so for example the delegation we have the concept of delegate enclosures.
and this is something that you can find in Swift you can find it in Catalan also or interesting yes.
and the coupling is another language on the JVM.
is this the same delegation that you were referring to when you said you could do method delegation?
or to another method in that case it's a delegation in the closure.
so a closure if it's an anonymous block of code so it's some kind of yeah.
for for Java JavaScript developers know that.
because you have those function anonymous function and then you have a body.
a closure is the same without having to declare all that function stuff.
you just have the body and that's all.
and inside that body you can have method calls.
and the delegation will say the delegation strategy will say to which object actually those method calls refer to.
so it's not something that you will find in Swift in particular.
but Swift has some concept of delegation Kotlin has some concept of delegation.
but the groovy concept of delegation is much larger actually than those languages.
so you can really really have some nice D essence just because of that delegation system.
and yeah, just to take another example of features that were borrowed from groovy in Swift.
you have that null safe operation yeah the it's called the Elvis operator and groovy.
just because of the to quit you know didn't doing but sterling I'm sorry in French so sometimes it's over.
yeah, in Java it's often a nightmare to deal with those null pointer exceptions.
just because you have to write if it is different from no then called then call method.
and groovy can simplify that let me say a few quotation not the quotation and interrogation mark.
so food interrogation market dot some method and then it will do the null check I say for you.
and this is this is incredibly simple way of dealing with objects that could potentially be no.
so reduces it removes the the code path where you have to do an if they if else yes.
so this is something that a lot of people are asking for in Java.
especially because in Java 8 you have that optional.
yeah, you tell other rapper or monad whatever you want to call it but it's not the same it's really not the same.
and especially optional involves a lot in terms of performance.
and what the the VM is able to do.
and in case of this operator we don't you we don't do that yet.
but potentially we can do some null type inference.
and totally remove the null checks in case we know that the object is not no.
it's not possible with something like optional.
so you have some performance implication in using optional types that you don't have if use de explicitly objects.
so in this case in a sense groovy written as idiomatic goofy can be faster than idiomatic Java.
for the same sort of check in theory it could.
but in practice it's not the case it's often not that case.
just because and in the end we compiled to bytecode.
and the Java ecosystem has at least the most widely-used a JVM.
which is the one provided by Oracle or the open JDK project.
so JVM has something which is called the JIT suggesting time compiler.
and this compiler is able to transform by code JVM bytecode into native byte code at runtime.
so it optimizes everything at runtime including optional checks.
no it's not capable of doing that font for the reason I explained.
so it's not capable of unfolding optional type.
but basically what it will recognize is Spartans of bytecode which are generated by Java compiler.
so if we generate by code which is different from what she is able to recognize it will not be optimized.
so this is this is really some interesting parts of designing a driven language.
which is sometimes you find some patterns of bytecode which are faster than what Java is able to produce.
but in practice it's often the opposite.
it's something that you have to do.
but since the Java language doesn't let you generate that kind of code.
you don't have optimizations available.
so you were talking about future improvements of the Java ecosystem.
and actually there is a there is own a Java announcements proposal which is help the JIT.
so basically it would let us designers of Javian languages.
to explain to the JIT what kind of patterns who generate.
so that it comes it can optimize them to interesting.
yeah, is this so this is a jsr I think?
yeah, I don't remember exactly but I think it's not the JSON that the GP some Java enhancement proposal.
but maybe I'm wrong maybe it's Jase aren't ready and I'm not sure.
no, okay, I'll try and link to that in the show notes.
related there was a now dormant jsr two-for-one from 2004.
which switch sawed it tried to standardize movie.
yeah, will that ever come back or will there ever be an attempt to make that happen again?
so it's very unlikely that it will come back.
so did basically there it's it's a huge very huge work did.
you write a specification of a language especially after the fact.
and so we had two options either we concentrated in improving the language spec fixing.
and/or designing and writing the specifications and we decided to go half way.
is we have significantly improved the documentation of the groovy language.
which was a major pain points for a lot of people recently.
that we have no new groovy documentation which kind of looks like a specification.
and when we say that it's actually that if you go to the groovy land website.
and that you read some documentation and that documentation contains a snippet of code.
you can make sure that actually it's tested.
so when we execute when we compile act really groovy.
we compile all the snippets of code that belong to the documentation.
so we document the language and the behavior of the language.
so specify the language after the fact by describing exactly how it behaves.
and since we have all those documentation snippets of code included in build actually.
if we ever break something the documentation is broken.
so we can make sure that we don't break and the behavior.
and existing behavior at the groovy language a strong regression suite.
yeah, so it's it's more than just documentation it's really explicit in everything with you.
and it's not as technical and as detailed as a pure specification.
as you can find in Java specification I see itself has this has the has this impacted the community size?
how big is the goofy community do we know is our way to measure?
so we don't have a clear figure of how big it is that we have some download figures.
and I think last year the groovy was downloaded almost 5 million times.
Wow, so that's really yeah there are a lot of people using groovy.
and I I would then say that lot of people use groovy without knowing it.
so if for example you used today if you do some Android programming.
and that you used a new build system actually you use Gradle.
so use groovy without knowing huge groovy.
mmm, if you use Jenkins for continuous integration.
Jenkins is deeply integrated with groovy.
you have that new wealth full system for example which is written groovy groovy DSL.
so you have groovy everywhere and very yet it's used in a lot of applications.
really in the big system scalable systems.
so you have you have some people saying that really doesn't Keynes really really not true.
I mean we have to prove that it's the opposite actually.
so I know that large companies like very large web companies like Netflix use it quite heavily.
yeah, that's that that is that is interesting for for example.
every time you click on that flex to to you to watch some episode.
it goes through delegation system which is written groovy.
so yeah, how many committers are there working on the language?
I mean how does it get maintained now that you're part of the ASF is?
so we are currently so we're negating to doing the Apache foundation.
which has a concept of what is a commit and active.
I would say the active committees people that.
write code often commit often in the codebase it's about six people.
but the committee of people contributing to the language is much larger than that.
and we have more than 100 people contributing to groovy.
and it comes it's yeah it comes from just contributing some I.
would suggest fixes in the documentation.
without having to you know the groovy card days itself.
you can just fix that documentation.
there are also people and contributing some small back fixes.
and it can come as far as complete new features.
so for example we have some new features around round compile to make the programming coming.
these are big features that involve the health code and those are user contributed.
so it's very very wide community and active community.
I see and you mentioned Android earlier.
one is one amazing thing you can do with Goofy these days is actually run it on Android.
can you think about that?
yeah, sure, so I would say that for people who are used to develop applications in Java on Android.
it's probably a nightmare if you know about Java 7 Java 8.
just because the code is very Java 5 stylish you know it's it's D.
yeah, I often say it's the anonymous in the class paradise.
you have anonymous classes everywhere boilerplate everywhere.
you have all those views that you have to bind you have to find a view by ID etc etc etc.
and actually what we wanted to do with groovy on Android.
is what we had done for groovy under on the desktop on the server.
so it's really remove all that boilerplate code that you have to write to create an Android application.
and I think we somehow managed to do that.
because we have some people who started using groovy for Android before it was actually official.
just because it removed so much boilerplate code that it was a pleasure again to develop applications on Android.
so the best example for that is the new New York Times application on the Google Play Store.
so that the new application is fully written in groovy.
wow, that's amazing that has a lot of users and a lot of users yes.
so it's yes really interesting to know that and really.
we have also an active community around that Android sub project.
so groovy itself is a language that can compile to JVM bytecode.
so we support Android now but in groovy since it's a language you have all those micro communities.
so we have the grace community we have the griffon community from the desktop.
and we have now that Android community.
and those people are writing new libraries that are designed to take advantage of the groovy language.
to make it very easy to write Android applications.
so for example the very arranging those annotations or those AC transformations to reduce the boilerplate code.
and not having to inject those views for examples it's just really simple example.
but you don't have to generate that code anymore.
so perhaps the number of downloads will be even bigger next year.
with now that we've got the these nucleus springing up.
we hope that but unfortunately now that we have mute move to the Apache foundation.
the download figures are going to be more difficult to get because of the mirrors.
you know in Apache Dahl the downloads are you know it's all on mirrors.
so you don't have download statistics now that a groovy is part of the Apache Software Foundation.
what do you see as once you're once you're past incubation and and the language is on track again.
what what do you think the next big features will be?
what's the next version of groovy look like?
yeah, so the next version of groovy the next major version of groovy groovy 3.
is probably going to abandon support for older JD case.
so that's because we want to leverage the full power of invoke dynamic.
so today we have that invade anemic run time.
but because of the history of the language and how it was designed.
how the meta object protocol was designed we cannot take advantage of the full power of in a dynamic and especially in terms of performance.
so we would like to redesign then the metal object protocol for it to be cleaner faster.
and leverage invoke dynamic fully.
and that requires us to abandon support for Java 7 Java 6 and Java 5.
would that mean that the Android port would no longer work?
yeah, today if we if you take a groovy code and that you compile it.
you can execute it in Java 6 and Java 7.
and that is really interesting for people that.
can it use for rhythm for example.
Java 8 and the lambda syntax you can you have the same groovy basically.
with the closures that you can have it on all the platforms in Java yeah. Java 6 I would say on Java 7.
and for groovy 3 probably been than that just because we need to be able to move forwards in terms of performance.
and to do that we cannot rely on the old protocol.
so it's going to be a big change.
and that's that's the long term development that we want you have a groovy.
but we have more features to come for that feature and that releases I would say so.
to dot something and yet one of them is the to five release.
which is probably going to bring in the new macro stuff.
and that macro stuff is a ste transformation simplified.
basically during runtime metric programming groove is very easy.
during compile time metaprogramming and especially st transformations is much harder.
because you have to know more about the compiler itself and how it works.
and what we want to do in groovy 2:5 it's simplified that using some kind of make rows.
and you could write a ste transformation much more easier that case ok.
well Cedric do you have anything you want to tell the listener anything you want to encourage them to check out?
where can they go to learn more about the GUI language for example?
yes, so the first thing obviously is to try the language. so it's really easy to do so.
if you are in the Linux you can use the JVM tool say it's G V M.
and it makes it very easy to install groovy and test it.
but obviously go check out the new website of groovy. so it's groovy - name.org.
and we have that new documentation which is really I think much much better than what was before.
but we also need your help.
I mean if you want to invest some time in a cool opens project just help us.
especially now that we're under the hood have the yeah.
we're in the Apache Software Foundation we can have no not much more broad development.
and open source development process.
so you can still contribute directly on github we have some mirrors and github if you want to.
but you can contribute some fixes or just help us reporting bugs.
just reporting base is very important.
so yeah, helpings can be just as easy as that you know submit pull requests or submit a bug report.
yeah, and what about you if they want to find out more about you or you on Twitter? do you have a website?
so I am yeah I am on Twitter online so it's seen like shampoo.
and I'm also github for hosting my blog post.
so the blog's the blog post I write are also on github.
so it's all open source I am a big fan of open.
so you can find all my blog and up on github.
and it's yeah they did probably going to paste the link to do to that and on the show notes.
but if you want if you want to have something which is written groovy and generates blog.
you can check out my own blog and you would have something which is really cool.
yeah, very cool.
ok, we'll have links to that in the show notes.
I think thank you very much Cedric for joining us today.
I hope it was worth your time.
thank you for if the invite it was very pleasant.
I'm good to talk to you dear listener.
we want to hear from you as always.
there are many different ways that you can reach us please feel free to comment on the show on our website. se - radio net.
you may email us at team at se - radio net.
or send us tweets on on the Twitter's at SU radio.
we're also on LinkedIn on Google+.
and we have a software engineering group where you can find us there.
and we're always as usual happy to hear from you.
with that I am Josh long thanks everyone for joining me and joining uh Cedric.
goodbye Cedric have a good day.
good day and thank you.
just thanks for listening to se Radio.
an educational program brought to you by I Triple E software magazine.
for more information about the podcast including other episodes visit our website at SE - radioman.
to provide feedback you can write comments on each episode on the website.
or write a review on itunes mention a message us on twitter at se radio.
or search for the software engineering radio group on Google+ or Facebook.
you can also email us a team at SES radio net.
this and all other episodes of SU radio is licensed under the creative commons 2.5 license.
thanks again for your support.
[Music]
[Applause]
you.
[Music]